Guide to the de Lévis Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
De Lévis family papers
1707-1850
MS 323
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
(5 boxes)
The papers contain legal documents, correspondence, and miscellaneous papers primarily concerned with Gaston-François-Christophe de Lévis, duc de Ventadour (1794-1863). The papers, in French, primarily relate to inheritance of land in Martinique.
De Lʹevis family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The de Lévis Family papers are mostly concerned with Gaston-François-Christophe de Lévis, duc de Ventadour (1794-1863). They contain legal documents, letters, court decisions, and other miscellaneous papers bearing directly with his inheritance case brought to court on Jan.29th,1831, and its later developments. The inheritance consists of certain estates in Martinique, originally the property of the d'Alesso family, de Lévis' grand-grandparents on his mother's side.
There are also manuscripts concerning many other members of both families, which bear directly or indirectly on the de Lévis case. These, however, come chronologically earlier and cover a span of about a century; from 1707 to circa 1810. Those after this date have to do with de Lévis' various affairs.
The documents first to be consulted are the printed booklet called "Mémoire" and all the other manuscripts to be found in the first Box, in the "Documents" folder. Therein are also included two charts of the de Lévis estates and a manuscript bearing the title "Note historique". For the sake of convenience, a genealogical table has been drawn based on this and other manuscripts. Short biographies about de Lévis' grandfather, father, and himself can be found in the 22nd vol. of La Grande Encyclopédie; Paris; Lamirault et Cie., eds; 1895-1896.
From the second folder on, material has been arranged chronologically and, wherever possible, according to content. (Thus, for example, the letters to the duc of de Lévis occupy a different folder than those by himself.) The first and earliest set of manuscripts are about Mme d'Ampus, presumably the first proprietor of the estates. These later on pass to M. Fabry and to M. Boutin from whom they are finally bought by the d'Alesso familiy. The other people under whose names the consequent manuscripts have been filed are members of the family to be found in the genealogical table.
Biographical / Historical
Gaston-François-Christophe de Lévis, 1794-1863: aide de camp to duc d'Angouléme; fought in the campaigns of Spain (1823) and Morée (1828); entered the Chambre des Paris in 1830; did not recognize Louis-Phillipe and went into exile with the old branches of the Bourbons; served as counselor to the comte de Chambord.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the De Levis family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
For short biographies of the De Levis family, please consult the Biographies.
Families; Inheritance and succession -- France; Europe; West Indies; De Lʹevis, Gaston François Christophe, 1794-1863; De Lʹevis family
- Inventory
  - Documents (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Succession de Madame d'Ampus, 1707-1803 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 4)
  - Fabry-Boutin affair, 1751-1788 (Box 2, Folder 5 - 7)
  - Mme. Gabrielle-Augustine-Michel Maréchal de Lévis (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - M. le Comte d'Ennery, 1775-1789 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Rose Bénédicte d'Alesso, Comtesse d'Ennery, 1802-1820 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Letters by the duc de Lévis, 1822-1847 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Letters to the duc de Lévis, 1802-1850 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The duc de Lévis cases, 1822-1850 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Tribunal -de Lévis - Thury, 1834-1835 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Cour Royale -de Lévis - Thury, 1834-1835 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - de Lévis; estates in Martinique, 1820-1846 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - de Lévis; accounts (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Other letters, 1771-1847 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified or undated manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 19)